<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Life of Michael Adrian de Ruyter, Admiral of Holland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12320808</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12320808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 189:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Life of Michael Adrian de Ruyter, Admiral of Holland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 115, [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ruyter, Michiel Adriaanszoon de, 1607-1676.</term>
               <term>United Provinces of the Netherlands. --  Zeemacht --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Admirals --  Netherlands --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:59474:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraved portrait of Michiel Adriaenszoon de Ruyter</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59474:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF <hi>Michael Adrian De R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>YTER</hi> ADMIRAL OF HOLLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Licenſed,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Octob.</hi> 1.</date>
                        <signed>Rog. L'Estrange.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the Kings Arms in the Poultrey, 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:59474:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59474:2"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF Admirall <hi>De Ruyter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ARts in all ages have had their Chiefs and Grandecs, who by inventing of new, or improving of old devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, have been eſteemed whilſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and renowned after death. And as their attempts were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to be valued but as the prevailing <hi>genius</hi> of their times weighed the uſes of them ſo ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ages according to their predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating meaſures, have placed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59474:3"/>or diſplaced their Artiſts in the <hi>Claſſis</hi> and Regiſter of fame; which ought indeed to be the Royal Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of ſuch Worthies praiſe; though fond Poſterity either over-affected with the advantages of their own, or not throughly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the uſefulneſs of elder-atchivements, do for the moſt part unjuſtly rank the Illuſtrious of former times in that order; that theſe have the precedency who ſeem moſt to favour the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the preſent applauded pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices: when antiquated contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances being tryed by a true ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of their profitableneſs when they Flouriſhed, and the advances they gained beyond their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Predeceſſors, may appear to have made as high a riſe above their antecedent hints, as our Great Guns excell the Roman bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Rams, or our roaring Trumpet-ſpeaker, old bauling <hi>Sten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> who now with the great He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59474:3"/>of diſtant ages are ſent again to School,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t pueris placeant &amp; declamatio fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The Maſters of the Military Art as well as others, being obnoxious to this ſevere and partiall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the contemporaries of great men have in all ages laboured to vindicate the honour of their He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, by bringing to a fair tryal of their Countrey, the attainments and feats of ſuch as they (the only competent Judges) thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be liſted in the Roll of Fame: and to crown them with ſuch Verdant Bayes as nothing but a hotter ſeaſon of newer attempts, and more taking diſcoveries, could ever blaſt or wither: And as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Navigators in coaſting of new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Lands, or Ingenious Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at the view of ſome rare and ſurpriſing beauty, fail not to make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59474:4"/>ſome tranſient deſignes of the new objects; that either misfortune might not altogether deprive the world of them, or that the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of others who ſhould have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opportunities might be raiſed to finiſh and compleat their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended draughts: So in all times ſome have been, who have left to poſterity the true and natural proportions and more diſcerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lineaments of the actions of famous men, which others who lived nearer them might fill up and imbelliſh with the ſeveral colours and ſhaddows of ſmaller occurrences. Now ſince our Age hath brought forth as many (if not more) Inſtances of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then any paſt, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them with as ſuitable ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and titles, as the moſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant times whatſoever: I thought it not amiſſe at this time, when every little Ale and Coffee-houſe <hi>Virtuoſo</hi> comes bluſtering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59474:4"/>upon us from the preſs; to give the world a view of the Life and Death of the late Renowned Sea-General <hi>Michael Ad. de Ruyter</hi> Lieutenant-Admiral of the States of the United Netherlands, whoſe rare Endowments and memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exploits have rendred him parallel to his moſt famed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors, and the high pitch to which he grew from ſo low a root, more conſpicuous then all: wherein if every little period of the ſeveral viciſſitudes and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his fortune, be not ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and punctually handled, as might be expected from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Diary, or <hi>Memoires</hi> (which is not the intent of this Treatiſe;) yet the more obſervable Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his whole life, partly from Relations of his own mouth, and partly from the authentick Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Witneſſes &amp; Records, ſhall be faithfully collected to the ſatisfaction of every Reader.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59474:5"/>
            <p>DUring the Wars betwixt the Spaniards and Dutch in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> there ſerved for ſome years the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> in quality of a private Trooper (a ſtranger by ſome judged a ſcottiſh man, ſo little known by his family, that his profeſſion gave him his Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name,) the happy Father of this brave man; who (being disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from, or diſpleaſed with that courſe of life;) with his wife, his only then childe <hi>Michael Ad. de Ruyter,</hi> born to him at <hi>Fluſhing</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> (the ſubject of this preſent Diſcourſe,) and ſerving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, being the whole of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, retired himſelf to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-houſe at two miles diſtance from <hi>Bergen ap Zome,</hi> and there to the quieter employment of a husbandmans life: where by his induſtrous endeavours, with two horſes, the greateſt part of his ſubſtance, in the uſuall labour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59474:5"/>of that Countrey, he ſupplied the wants of his family with care and pains: but neither the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the poor mans fortune (which commonly begets either contempt or pity) nor yet the priviledge of his perſon, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſometime ſerved under the ſame Enſignes; could ſecure him or his beaſts from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of licentious Souldiers: his two horſes are taken from him by force; and carried to the Dutch Camp in <hi>Flanders,</hi> by ſome of the Troopers of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: this loſs was too conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be neglected by him, who thereby ſaw himſelf and family utterly ruined: He therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens after them to the camp; but finding his addreſſes for juſtice fruitleſs, by the delays and neglect of the Officers, and being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the proceedings of looſly diſciplined or ill-paid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, where the Commanders
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59474:6"/>either ſhare in, or connive at the rapine of the Souldiers: he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on a ſpeedier and more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al way of reparation, by ſtealing from robbers what they had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly forced from him: And ſo having diſcovered where his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were at graſs, watching his opportunity, he ſecretly conveyed them away, and left them in a place ſomewhat remote from his own houſe, where he judged them fartheſt from danger, foreſeeing (as indeed it happened) that theſe new Maſters would not fail to look after the ſtrays. The ſouldiers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing there booty, and concluding that the owner had them, returned in the night with a purpoſe to finde them at his houſe; but being by his provident care diſappointed; in barbarous revenge they ſet on fire the poor ſingle thatcht Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe about the ears of the help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Inhabitants; In the horrour of this ſudden ſurpriſe, whilſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59474:6"/>the father, mother and ſervant ſave themſelves, by breaking through the mercileſs flames, with that care of ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is common to all creatures, and aſtoniſhment, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in ſuch unexpected frights; the poor harmleſs childe the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture darling of <hi>Neptune,</hi> lay at the mercy of devouring <hi>Vulcan</hi> faſt aſleep in an upper room, ſwadled in his cradle; but the flames of Parental love towards an only childe, ſtronger than thoſe of fire, ſoon ſcorcht the mothers heart with ſo great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the danger of her Son; that aided by that provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which ſaved the Children in the fiery furnace, with more than maſculine courage, ſhe threw her ſelf into the houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to ſave or die with that childe, by whoſe life and death fortune had decreed her honour: and having in her petticoat,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59474:7"/>through ſmoke and flames, got into the upper Room, firſt threw the childe out of the window in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſheet held by the father and maid to receive him, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward jump't out her ſelf, ſaving from that little <hi>Troy</hi> her young <hi>Aeneas.</hi> So croſs and unlucky are many times the beginnings of virtuous Men, and low the <hi>baſis</hi> of Fames <hi>Pyramides,</hi> miſery being commonly the firſt ſtep to happineſs, and a gloomy morning the portal of a fair day: Having thus happily avoided the Fury of this cruel Element, though ſtript of all, naked as truth it ſelf, the diſconſolate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this ſo great uncertainty, finding no other hopes of relief but the Charity of the Merciful, betook himſelf with his wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Family to <hi>Bergen ap Zome</hi> the next Town of Note, where arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving early in the morning, he preſented to his compaſſionate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59474:7"/>Countreymen a lamentable ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of his new diſaſter:</p>
            <p>The commendable care of that Countrey in providing for the Neceſſities of the indigent, either by maintaining of the infirm and impotent, or by imploying the ſtronger and thoſe that are able, to work: afforded means for the poor man to ſubſiſt and feed his family; untill his young ſon being grown up to the ſtate of a boy, able to do ſomewhat for himſelf, was placed in the rope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground of the Heer <hi>Lampſon</hi> in <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> a conſiderable Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant; who had a Manufactory of Ropes there: The poor childe complying with the condition which he could not alter, with ſeveral other boys of his own rank and age, dilligently follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his buſineſs in ſpinning of rope-yarn, and other drudgeries of that vocation to the content of his Overſeers; until ſome time
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59474:8"/>after, the Heer <hi>Lampſon</hi> himſelf coming into the rope-ground, and eying the lad; his fancy ſuggeſted to him (obſerving the features and carriage of the boy) the unſuitableneſs of that trade to the <hi>genius</hi> of the lad: and finding upon examination the forwardneſs of his wit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident readineſs in his anſwers, and his willingneſs to leave that courſe, and to ſerve him in ſome other capacity; he releaſed him from that ſlavery, and ſent him to ſchool; where in a ſhort time he gave ſuch pregnant proofs of his parts and induſtry, that his Maſter finding his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency ripe for employment, prudently at firſt intruſted him with the charge of keeping of the accounts of his family-expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo he might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have a tryal of the youths abilities, and prevent the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, into which higher ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59474:8"/>and diſtance of place often miſleads unexperienced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners; imitating herein the example of Falconers, who uſe firſt to call their hawks to their fiſts with a guard, before they venture them at large to the lure: In this office he carried himſelf with ſo great fidelity and diſcretion, and thereby gained ſo great eſteem from his Maſter; that he advanced him to be his book-keeper, and to the management of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-affairs: wherein being likewiſe much ſatisfied with his skill and diligence; he pitched upon him as a perſon every way qualified for a Factor in his trade in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which conſiſted in but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, herrings, tallow and hides: and accordingly ſent him to <hi>Dublin;</hi> There he lived ſeven years under the inſpection of Mr <hi>Cremor,</hi> Mr <hi>Vanhorn,</hi> Mr <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> and ſome others of his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59474:9"/>Maſters Correſpondents; during which ſpace, beſides his attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Engliſh Tongue (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary to him who was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to treat ſo often with the Engliſh in their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) he gave ſo great proofs of his dexterity in the conduct of affairs of Trading, and of his faithfulneſs to his truſt, and thereby ſo much content to his Maſter and Correſpondents; that by them he was ſent into the <hi>Streights,</hi> to negotiate as <hi>Supercargo</hi> of their Concerns there. And whilſt in his ſeveral Voyages from Port to Port in thoſe parts, he ſucceſsfully improved his traffick to the profit both of his Maſter and himſelf; being a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural enemy to idleneſs, and an Unactive life, and totally averſe from the lazy and bruitiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellings of the moſt part of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; he had leiſure to rub up thoſe few impreſſions and hints
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59474:9"/>of the Mathematicks, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Navigation, which he had learned when a boy: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the ripeneſs of his wit, his conſtant pains and ſtudy, and the aſſiſtance of ſome Artiſts, in a ſhort time he made ſuch lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable progreſs; that he not only became able to conduct any Ship himſelf, but obtained a great Name amongſt Navigators. And having afterward made ſeveral Voyages into the <hi>Streights</hi> and <hi>Barbary,</hi> upon the account of the Heer <hi>Lampſon</hi> his Maſter and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor, with conſtant good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and applauſe, he married a Widow, and ſetled himſelf in <hi>Fluſhing</hi> in <hi>Zealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The many good ſervices which he had performed to his Maſter, and the reputation gained in his Sea-expeditions, began to plain the way to his preferment: In the year 1650. the dayly dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages received from the <hi>Corſairs</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59474:10"/>of <hi>Argiers,</hi> the enemies of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> being ſo ſenſible, that thereby the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Trade, of great advantage to that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was much obſtructed: the States (for the ſecurity of their Merchants) reſolved to ſend Convoys with their Ships: the Heer <hi>Lampſon</hi> laying hold of this opportunity to ſerve his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and at the ſame time to ſhow his love and gratitude to his friend, by the cheapeſt, and yet moſt noble way of reward; ſo effectually recommended Mr <hi>De Ruyter</hi> to the <hi>States General,</hi> that he obtained for him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to be Captain of a Man of War appointed by them, as a Convoy for their Merchant-men in the <hi>Streights,</hi> thoſe fatal Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas, the Hercules-pillars of his life and honour, where he began and ended his Sea-prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and gave the firſt and laſt proofs of his Conduct and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59474:10"/>
            <p>In this expedition he had the Occaſion to lay the foundation of his future greatneſs, firſt, by rendring himſelf remarkable in his Command, and next in his Eſtate, the two uſual handmaids of riſing fortunes: for as by his Valour and Conduct in many ſucceſsful Engagements with theſe Pirates, he procured the one, ſo by his lawful and honeſt endeavours, he miſſed not of the other. Inſomuch that his Name being grown publick in <hi>Holland,</hi> by the dayly characters of thoſe who had been obliged by his care and good offices; the States began to think him worthy of ſome higher rank.</p>
            <p>The Occaſion was not long wanting to his more proſperous fortune, For in <hi>anno</hi> 1652. the equal ſucceſs of the two Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Common-wealths of <hi>England</hi> (then too unhappily eſtabliſhed) and the States of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59474:11"/>the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands</hi> more deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted; began to advance to the incompatible heighth of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority (which was as much as Supremacy) their pretenſions on the Seas: And although their claims were as different as that of an old poſſeſſor from a new intruder; yet the younger Rival the <hi>Hollanders</hi> thinking their power not inferiour to the other, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of long and uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted poſſeſſion, demanded of them the uſual ſubmiſſions: reſolved to diſpute the right by force of Arms, and ſo broke forth a War; which for the eagerneſs of the parties, the frequency of engagements, and the undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſtancy of the adverſaryes whilſt it laſted; may juſtly take place of all which before that time enobled the Ocean. Now was Captain <hi>Michael Adr. De Ruyter</hi> (ſignalized for his good
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59474:11"/>ſervices in the Mediterranean, and eyed by the States as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon fit for greater action) called home: And whilſt Old Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> (after the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the nineteenth of <hi>May,</hi> 1652. with General <hi>Blake</hi> off of <hi>Dover</hi>-rode, the firſt action of hoſtility in this war, where he was defeated with the loſs of two Ships and many men) was equipping and preparing in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> his Fleet, and broom to ſweep the Seas; <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a ſquadron of Fifty Men of War was ſpeeded out from <hi>Zealand,</hi> to Convoy the Merchant-men to the Weſtward out of danger; and to ſcowr the Seas of the Engliſh; who on that ſide rendred the Navigation unſafe: This great Fleet firſt appearing off of <hi>Bright Hamſtead</hi> in <hi>Suſsex,</hi> where they forced aſhoar, and took ſeveral Barks, continued their courſe Weſtward by the back of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59474:12"/>the <hi>Iſle of Wight:</hi> Advice of this being brought to the pretended Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> who then Commanded a Fleet of fourty Men of War in the Weſt about <hi>Plymouth;</hi> was ordered to ſtretch over the Channel towards the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> to hinder, or at leaſt diſpute them their paſſage: this he accordingly obeying, on the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1652. the two Fleets came in ſight; and about four in the afternoon, to blows; and here continued a ſharp Fight, bravely maintained on both ſides, till ſeparated by night, both lay by: But <hi>De Ruyters</hi> chief buſineſs being to ſecure his Merchant-men, and Sir <hi>George</hi> not thinking it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to renew the Engagement: he carried off his Fleet without loſs of a Ship.</p>
            <p>The States acquainted with his good Conduct in this Firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59474:12"/>appointed him his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the mouth of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, to ſtop and ſeize all Engliſh Ships homeward or outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound: There he diſcharged an Engliſh Ship that he had taken, upon condition that the Maſter ſhould acquaint Sir <hi>George Ayſcue,</hi> that he ſtayed for him, and would be glad to ſee him: but Sir <hi>George</hi> knowing well the prudence and valour of the Commander, and the humour of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> not raſh to run any apparent risk on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for oſtentation of bravery, his own Fleet being inferior in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and having received no new Orders from his Maſters; returned no anſwer: This brisk carriage won <hi>De Ruyter</hi> a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reputation of gallantry and good conduct from the States-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but in particular manner from the States of <hi>Zealand:</hi> In this ſtation he continued cruiſing, till <hi>De Witt</hi> with another conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59474:13"/>Fleet from <hi>Holland</hi> joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, on the Twenty fourth of <hi>September;</hi> and having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſix Plate ſhips with their convoy whom they expected from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> they both together ſet ſail homewards.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Blake</hi> returning with the Engliſh Fleet from <hi>Plymouth</hi> towards the <hi>Downs,</hi> diſcovered the Dutch Fleet commanded by <hi>De Witt</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> riding at the back of the <hi>Goodwin-Sands,</hi> after that they had ſent their charge into <hi>Holland; Blake</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have engaged them, but the winde blowing hard hindred his attempt then untill afterward; the ſeaſon being more favourable on the Twenty eighth of <hi>October,</hi> with three Squadrons of Ships he made up to them; but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them ſo well protected by the Sands amongſt which they rode, and having run aground the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign</hi> and <hi>Reſolution,</hi> (which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59474:13"/>were preſently got off again) in his too raſh approach with the great Ships, he was forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. <hi>De Witt</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> in the entry of a War being aſhamed thus to be braved, voluntarily left their advantagious ſtation, came forth and fought the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; but with ſo great loſs, that notwithſtanding all the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and conduct employed by the two Admiralls during the action, they were forced to run, leaving many Ships burnt and ſunk; and were purſued by the Engliſh within twelve Leagues, E. S. E. of the <hi>Maes,</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Holland;</hi> till with the remainder of the Fleet ſhattered and torn <hi>de Wit</hi> and <hi>de Ruyter</hi> got into <hi>Goree.</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted their ill ſucceſſe in this Fight to the over-match of the Engliſh, and the cowardiſe of ſome of their Captains, who did not fight; but experience hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59474:14"/>ſince demonſtrated, that the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent uſe which the cautious <hi>De Ruyter</hi> made of the misfortune, was never to forſake an advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtation till a more advantagious opportunity of fighting offfered.</p>
            <p>This Defeat ſpurr'd the <hi>Dutch</hi> on revenge: For on the Nine and twentieth of <hi>November</hi> following, old <hi>Van Trump</hi> and Vice-Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a Fleet of Eighty Men of War, and Ten Fire-ſhips put to Sea again, and finding Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Blake</hi> at his ſtation with a number far inferiour, not much exceeding fourty Sail, but with equal reſolution to fight: <hi>Van Trump</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> made up towards him, and he not ſhrinking, there began a hot and bloudy combat, obſtinatly maintained for ſome time; but the diſparity of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber being unreaſonably great, the Engliſh were routed, and the Garland-Frygat taken: In this Fight <hi>De Ruyter</hi> ſuſtained much
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59474:14"/>dammage in his Ship, and loſt many men, having been obſerved as forward in the Engagement as any, and as long in action.</p>
            <p>The Dutch in the mean time kept the Seas, cruiſing in the Channel off of the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> whilſt <hi>Blake</hi> impatient of long delay, having with great expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fitted and reinforced his Fleet: the Eight of <hi>February</hi> 1653. ſet ſail from <hi>Quinborough</hi> with ſixty Men of War, intending to joyn twenty more at <hi>Portſmouth.</hi> Theſe keen Competitors ſeemed only to withdraw a little, and take breath, that with greater force, and fury, they might renew their onſet, as it proved ſhortly after: For <hi>Van Trump</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſailed according to his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Weſtward, to attend and Convoy a Numerous and Rich Fleet of Merchant-men, coming from the <hi>Streights,</hi> and other Southern parts; and on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59474:15"/>the eleventh of <hi>February</hi> General <hi>Blake</hi> having joyned the <hi>Portſmouth</hi> Fleet at <hi>Beachy-head,</hi> he ſailed the height of <hi>Portland,</hi> and there lay croſs the <hi>Channel,</hi> expecting the coming of the <hi>Dutch:</hi> On the Eighteenth, about break of day, were diſcovered <hi>Van Trump</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with their Fleet, to the number of between three and four hundred Sail, Men of War and Merchant-men: The Engliſh ſtoutly bore up and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged them, and were with no leſs valour received by the Dutch; but <hi>Blake</hi> reſolving to make them ſenſible, that it was not their courage, but number, which had given the Engliſh the former ruffle; preſſed them with ſuch irreſiſtable courage and force, that they were forced to run, and with great loſs to get home; yet the conduct and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of <hi>Van Trump</hi> and <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was ſo remarkable in bringing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59474:15"/>off the Merchant-men; that both merited and received ſpecial and publick thanks from the States.</p>
            <p>By this time the Hollanders having by freſh experience lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the danger of tempting the Lion even in his den, reſolved no more to hazard their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-men in the Channel; but judged the fartheſt way about to be the neareſt way home; and ſo having ordered them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn by the back of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> Leiutenant Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> and Vice-Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> were ſet out from the <hi>Texel</hi> with Eighty Men of War to meet and Convoy a Fleet of Two hundred Sail of Merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men coming that way from <hi>France:</hi> which being ſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effected without interruption from the Engliſh then in the <hi>Downs,</hi> they kept out at ſea expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting their Enemies. The Engliſh then being commanded by a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59474:16"/>of Generals of equal and joynt authority, <hi>Blake, Dean,</hi> and <hi>Monck,</hi> on the ſecond of <hi>Iune,</hi> came in ſight of the Dutch Fleet, and about eleven or twelve of the Clock engaged them. It was fought till night with much blood and fierce reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; but the Engliſh accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to victory, having loſt <hi>Dean,</hi> one of their Generals, ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them ſo warmly, that they thought it ſafeſt to fly to <hi>Blanck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enburgh;</hi> General <hi>Monck</hi> purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them at the heels to ſeven fathom water. During the whole fight Vice-Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and Rear-Admiral <hi>Lawſon</hi> on the Engliſh ſide, having ſingled themſelves out, fought ſingly with ſuch courage and emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as might be expected from two Commanders of ſo much Fame and Honour.</p>
            <p>Hardly can there be ſhown greater ſtruglings for Victory,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59474:16"/>or ſtiffer ambition for greatneſs, than appeared in the Dutch, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all this War; who the more they were beaten (like balls againſt a wall) the ſooner they rebounded: About the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>Iuly, Van Trump</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> from <hi>Zealand,</hi> and <hi>De Witt</hi> from <hi>Holland,</hi> ſet out again to ſea; and being joyned, made up a Fleet of Ninety Sail of Men of War, and ten Fireſhips. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Monck</hi> with a Fleet far leſs in number being then abroad, the twenty nineth of <hi>Iuly</hi> towards night came up with them: but the Maſter of his Ship fearing the enemies Fireſhips, and advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him not to venture an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, the General in anger, and in terms more of a ſtout Commander, than expert Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; bid him <hi>Turn again:</hi> And ſo with prodigious courage gave them their laſt, and moſt fatal defeat, in theſe their Wars with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59474:17"/>the Commonwealth of <hi>England:</hi> wherein beſides the loſs of Twenty ſix Men of War, their Admiral <hi>Van Trump</hi> ended his daies; and of all the Flagſhips of their Fleet only that of <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> had the fortune to come into Port with the Flag ſtanding.</p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Van Trump, Opdam</hi> was made Admiral in his place, a Land-Souldier and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Horſe; the States proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thinking, that by matching the quality of their Admiral with that of the Engliſh General <hi>Monck;</hi> they might equal their fortune: <hi>De Witt</hi> Vice-Admiral, and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> Rear-Admiral of <hi>Holland.</hi> But whilſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> are fitting for new action, though with ſomewhat ſlower procedure than formerly, their heat and ſtrength being much, cooled and abated; there ſtarts up in <hi>England</hi> a new Statholder; <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> General of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59474:17"/>Army made Protector of the Common-wealth. This New Uſurper, knowing that his authority being forced, violent, and againſt nature, needed grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confirmation and ſupport, than he could expect from the free and voluntary obedience of an overpowered people: and the States general finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much weakened by the paſt War, they both underſtood one another ſo well, and their ſeveral intereſts, that about the latter end of <hi>January</hi> 1653/4. a peace was concluded betwixt them, which at that time ſtopt the troubled humours, but remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the cauſes of relapſes.</p>
            <p>After this peace, <hi>De Ruyter</hi> tranſports himſelf with his Wife, Son <hi>Engell De Ruyter,</hi> two daughters, and the reſt of his family, from <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> where he had formerly lived, to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> as the place of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59474:18"/>reſidence, and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous ſtage of Honour: but here he had hardly warmed his new Houſe, when the States found new buſineſs for him in the <hi>Old Streights.</hi> The Pirates of theſe Seas after their wonted manner ſo incommoded Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in theſe parts, that <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a Squadron of Men of War in <hi>anno</hi> 1654. was ſent by the States to ſuppreſs and tame their inſolency: In his Voyage thither he friendly met with his ancient enemy <hi>Blake,</hi> who then was in the <hi>Streights</hi> with a Fleet of Ships upon the account of the Protector and Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> where they ſaluted each other, ſhook hands, and parted in very good terms; and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> continuing his courſe to <hi>Argiers;</hi> in a ſhort time ſo humbled the <hi>Corſairs</hi> of that place, <hi>Tripoli</hi> and <hi>Tunnis,</hi> that he brought them to a peace,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59474:18"/>though of ſhort duration, and ſo with honour and applauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned back again to <hi>Holland:</hi> where ſhortly after a greater field of honour was deſigned for him.</p>
            <p>Men that would be great and rich by hook and by crook, by potching, and fiſhing where ſometime they ſhould not; firſt grow envious and pettiſh, and then angry and quarrelſome with their thriving Neighbours. In the year 1657. the Victorious Arms of <hi>Swedland</hi> had lodged themſelves in the very heart of <hi>Poland,</hi> threatning danger if not ruine to that Kingdom. The States of <hi>Holland</hi> fearing leſt the proſperous ſucceſs of that Crown with which their friendſhip and correſpondence was always doubtful and uncertain, might keep bread from their butter, and much damnifie their traffick in the Baltick Sea: perſwaded
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59474:19"/>the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Allie, who had more reaſon then force, to break with <hi>Swed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> promiſing him all aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to regain from that King what he had wreſted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from him ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: This inſtance of the States-General ſo prevailed with him, that he declared War againſt the King of <hi>Swedland,</hi> and invaded his Kingdomes; wherewith the <hi>Swede</hi> being allarmed, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to leave <hi>Poland,</hi> and with all his forces return home againſt the <hi>Dane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bad ſucceſs which the <hi>Danes</hi> had in theſe Wars both by Sea and land, obliged the States of <hi>Holland</hi> to put a Fleet to Sea under the command of Admiral <hi>De Witt</hi> to aſſiſt them in the <hi>Sound;</hi> But his Fleet being by the <hi>Swedes</hi> there routed, the Admirals Ship the <hi>Bredrow</hi> ſunk, and <hi>De Witt</hi> himſelf either killed or drowned:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59474:19"/>a freſh Recruit was diſpatched with Admiral <hi>Opdam</hi> to re-inforce their Fleet: <hi>Opdam</hi> arrived in the <hi>Sound,</hi> but finding himſelf too weak to encounter the enemy; was forced to ſecure himſelf and Fleet in <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> then blockt up by the <hi>Swedes</hi> with a ſtrait Siege, both by Sea and land: The King of <hi>Swedland</hi> in the mean time hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of greater preparations in <hi>Holland</hi> for a ſtronger Fleet to be ſent under the command of <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> whoſe conduct and fortune was more apprehended then that of the others, ordered his Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> vigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proſecute with the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Oliver,</hi> their inſtances for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance: This they ſo accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the intended ſuccours (his death preventing) were by him recommended to the care of his Son <hi>Richard,</hi> the ſhort Succeſſour to his Uſurped autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: <hi>Richard</hi> with the conſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59474:20"/>of the then pretended Parliament, for that end, and for the ſecurity of the Engliſh Trade in the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> in the beginning of the year 1659. ſent the brave General <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague,</hi> afterward Earl of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> with fourty Men of Warr well mann'd, and ſome Fire-ſhips, who on the twenty ſeventh of <hi>April,</hi> arrived in the <hi>Sound:</hi> Shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came alſo <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a ſtrong Fleet from <hi>Holland,</hi> whoſe preſence relieved <hi>Copenhagen</hi> and <hi>Opdams</hi> Fleet; For the <hi>Swedes</hi> not being able alone to come to a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the Engliſh refuſing to fight until they were ſatisfied in ſome demands, and the news of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (Richard</hi> the Protector being turned out of power) ſuperve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the ſame inſtant, which called them home again, relieved the Beſieged, and hindred a new rupture betwixt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59474:20"/>muſt have immediately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> by this timely ſuccour revived, and the Engliſh Fleet returned to <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Opdam</hi> to <hi>Holland; De Ruyter</hi> with the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Fleet continued Maſter of the Seas, ready for ſome Land-undertaking, ſince the <hi>Swedes</hi> (then too weak) declined all engaging at Sea: The Iſland of <hi>Funnen</hi> in the <hi>Baltick Sea,</hi> of the ancient inheritance of the <hi>Danes,</hi> but then in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> being taken by them ſome years before, offered a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary occaſion: And for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe General <hi>Schaack,</hi> with ſeven thouſand men, being put aboard of the Fleet at <hi>Kiel,</hi> were by <hi>De Ruyter</hi> conducted; and on the laſt of <hi>October</hi> landed at <hi>Kortemundor,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Funnen:</hi> The <hi>Swedes</hi> made brave reſiſtance; but <hi>De Ruyter</hi> diverting their Forces, with alarming at the ſame time
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59474:21"/>other parts of the Iſland, and with a ſtout example, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtanding in the water, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the Souldiers to land, whom in great numbers they poured aſhoar; The <hi>Swedes</hi> were overthrown with great loſſe, and the Iſland regained to the <hi>Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This brave action of <hi>De Ruyter</hi> gained him more reputation from his Countrey, and honour from his maſters, then all which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time he had atchieved, and ſo endeared him to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and eſteem of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> that he honoured him with the higheſt Order of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of that Kingdom, being that of the Elephant; and preſented him with a Chain and Meddal of Gold, which afterward he wore; and having remained there among the <hi>Swedes,</hi> untill the Peace between the <hi>Danes</hi> and them in <hi>May.</hi> 1660. was ratified,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59474:21"/>he with great applauſe returned with his Fleet home.</p>
            <p>The War betwixt the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Swedes</hi> ended, and <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> with his Fleet ſafely returned into <hi>Holland,</hi> new loſſes from the Pirates of <hi>Argiers, Tripoli,</hi> and <hi>Tunis,</hi> called afreſh to the States for remedy: The vigilant and ſucceſsful <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was by the States deſigned for that charge; whoſe good ſervices (on the like occaſion) even in the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Sea-command had been remarkable in thoſe Seas; and is therefore diſpatcht with a Squadron of Ships into the <hi>Streights;</hi> where he kept rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Fleet, purſuing and preſſing thoſe <hi>Gorſairs</hi> with ſo great care and ſucceſs, that the benefit of his conſtant pains and valour became ſenſible to all the Merchants who traded there; whereby he confirmed to himſelf that fame and reputation which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59474:22"/>he had heretofore ſo juſtly meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, until matters of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern called him thence, upon the occaſion following.</p>
            <p>After the wonderfull and long-wiſhed-for re-eſtabliſhment of his Majeſty, the King of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> in the Throne of his Anceſtors, from which by the madneſs of his Subjects he had been long baniſhed; the States of the United Provinces overgrown with the wealth and proſperity of many years peace, the ordinary promoters of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; being conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that their carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Neighbors, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Engliſh, however cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, could not but breed ſuch jealouſies as muſt in time break forth into open enmity; and perceiving his Majeſty of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> already ſo diſſatisfied with their diſguiſed practiſes, as could not but of neceſſty produce
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59474:22"/>a War, reſolved to bring it to a tryall as ſoon as poſſibly they could, by giving the firſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of rupture, under the pretext of being provok'd by injuries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiny,</hi> and elſewhere; Hereupon they Ordered Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with a ſquardron of thirteen Men of War then at <hi>Gibraltor</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to make ſail for the Coaſt of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and to ſet upon the Engliſh there; This he ſo effectually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that in a ſhort time he deſtroyed moſt of their Factories, took <hi>Cormanteen</hi> Caſtle with other places, ſeverall Ships and goods belonging to the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>That action ſo incenſed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> that war was thereupon in <hi>anno</hi> 1664. publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaimed againſt the States General of the United Provinces, impowering all his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to uſe againſt them their ſubjects and people, all acts of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59474:23"/>hoſtility; but whilſt this was do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home, <hi>De Ruyter</hi> diligent in the purſuance of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion abroad, attempted the burning of the Engliſh Ships at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> but in vain; and from thence ſailing to <hi>New-found land,</hi> took ſeveral Merchants Ships, ſtript the men, and left them without proviſions; an act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the name of ſo brave a man: Thus whilſt <hi>Opdam</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of the Dutch Fleet in <hi>June</hi> 1665, having engaged his Royall Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> was in fire and ſmoak hurried out of this world, and his Fleet beat home with great loſs of Ships and men; <hi>De Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> remained at Sea, annoying the Ships and Foreign Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Engliſh: But <hi>Opdams</hi> death rendred his preſence at home abſolutely neceſſary, his experience and ſucceſs in War being ſo well known to all, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59474:23"/>the univerſal voice of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple daily called his Name, whom (according to the intereſt and power they pretend to upon the Seas) they adopted, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, <hi>Son of Neptune:</hi> Advice was therefore ſent to him, that he ſhould with his Fleet haſten home with all expedition; which he obeying, ſlily ſlipt by the Engliſh Fleet wrapt in miſt, as men with their cloaks about their mouths ſhun the company of thoſe whom they are not willing to meet; And on the laſt of <hi>July</hi> 1665. ſafely arrived in the <hi>Emmes:</hi> his arrival was congratulated by the States, and he thereupon made Admiral, but with authority not ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, but that he was ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the Triumvirate of <hi>De Witt, Huygens</hi> and <hi>Bureel;</hi> who according to a new Model, had the ſuperintendency of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall affairs. He was no ſooner
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59474:24"/>inſtalled in his new Command, but <hi>Auguſt</hi> 13. with a Fleet of Ninety Sail of Men of War, he was Ordered out from the <hi>Texel,</hi> to ſecure and convoy home the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Fleet, and many other rich Merchant-men, which ſtopt at <hi>Bergen</hi> for fear of the Engliſh Fleet then at Sea under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich;</hi> and who had been put in great alarm by the brave, but fruitleſs attempt of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Tiddyman,</hi> who was ſent out to have ſeized them in their harbour; In his going he met not with the Engliſh Fleet, but in his return was diſcovered and attacqued by the Earl of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> who finding himſelf too weak, his charge great, and the windes very high, with a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Fight he made the beſt of his way, and with the loſs of two great <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships, ſome other Merchant-men, and five
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59474:24"/>Men of War, he brought his Fleet into the Weſt <hi>Emmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before his Arrival by a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a Ship which he had met at Sea, he ſent a challenge to Major <hi>Holmes</hi> to meet him there; that ſeeing they two had been the firſt Adventurers in the War, they might try the ſucceſs of the publick quarrel, as far as their particular proweſs and fortune could incline it: The Challenge was as nobly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the Major, as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly and gallantly ſent by <hi>De Ruyter;</hi> and the King of <hi>England</hi> to encourage the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, Knighted Major <hi>Holmes,</hi> and aſſigned him a ſtately New Ship then built at <hi>Deptford</hi> which he purpoſely called the <hi>Defiance:</hi> but this combat was diverted by other intervening accidents.</p>
            <p>In <hi>May</hi> 1666. <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with his Fleet being at Sea, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſet out a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59474:25"/>well appointed and great Fleet, under the joint Command of his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and his Grace the Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle,</hi> renowned for his valour and ſucceſs in the former War againſt the Dutch, and now advanced to that title; for the great and memorable Services performed to the King: but a falſe rumour of the French be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Sea, occaſioned the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that Fleet: for Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with the white Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, being ordered to make for the coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conjunction of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> who before the French came to Sea, the Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> was left, with about fifty Sail of Men of War, to wait on the Dutch: The boundleſs courage of that Duke, a diſpiſer of danger, led him to a gallant, but raſh attempt, upon <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and his Fleet,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59474:25"/>who then riding at anchor off of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> with a number of Ships far exceeding the Engliſh; was upon Fryday the firſt of <hi>June</hi> ſo unexpectedly aſſaulted by them, the winde blowing high; that many of his Ships were fain to cut their cables in haſte to put themſelves in order of fighting: This was indeed a bloody and terrible engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which continued with matchleſs fury and reſolution on both ſides, till Sunday in the Evening; when the Engliſh Fleet being much torn, and the Generals own Ship diſabled; (the diſproportion of number, and the enemies Fleet being to the Leeward, whereby they played their great guns, which the Engliſh could not, being to the weather, and the winde high; giving great advantage to the Dutch) they drew off, having loſt the evening, before
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59474:26"/>the brave Ship the <hi>Prince,</hi> which being ſtranded, was burnt by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> Commander made Priſoner: yet notwithſtanding their great loſs, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> upon notice given, and the noiſe of the guns then heard, having on Sunday in the Evening rejoyned the Fleet, and given the uſuall proofs of his great and undaunted valour: both Generalls on Munday early in the morning, purſued the Dutch, who were almoſt out of ſight, paſſed and repaſſed their Fleet ſeveral times: But <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> finding himſelf (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the recruits received) ſo weakned, that his longer continuance in action might have produced the effects rather of a vain glorious Bravo, then of a prudent circumſpect General, and good Countrey-man; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given wonderfull marks of his carriage and conduct, made
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59474:26"/>made what haſte he could to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Fleet: This was the firſt encounter that <hi>De Ruyter</hi> as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief had with the Engliſh in theſe Wars; the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of which was equally cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in both Nations, but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever had the better, it is certain, both ſuſtained very great loſſes.</p>
            <p>The pretenſions to victory in this laſt Fngagement owned mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually by both parties, occaſioned their haſtening out again with all ſpeed to Sea, either to make good the old, or to gain a new title; and ſo in <hi>Iuly</hi> both Fleets were abroad; The <hi>Engliſh</hi> commanded by <hi>Albemarle,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> by <hi>De Ruyter;</hi> And on S. <hi>Iames's</hi> day about nine in the morning met and fell to blows again. <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> with his Fleet for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time made a brisk and a ſtout reſiſtance, but the Engliſh jealous of their honour which ſeemed to ſuffer by the <hi>Dutch</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59474:27"/>to themſelves the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the former Engagement, plyed them ſo fiercely, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident <hi>De Ruyter</hi> finding his fleet in a bad condition, according to his ſaving principles, of making the beſt of an ill bargain, began to give way, and was ſo cloſely purſued by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Red and White Squadrons (whileſt <hi>Van Trump</hi> couragiouſly entertained the Blew) that <hi>De Ruyters</hi> own Ship was much ſhattered, and himſelf in all probability, if the Engliſh great ſhips could have got up with him, in danger of being taken, and two ſquadrons of his Fleet utterly deſtroyed: In this fight, on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſide, were only three Captains killed, the <hi>Reſolution</hi> burnt, and not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny above three hundred men kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and wounded: On the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſide (according to the general computation of that time) above four thouſand men killed, three
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59474:27"/>hundred common Sea-men wounded, and many Captains ſlain, amongſt which <hi>Everſon</hi> Admiral of <hi>Zeland, Dirickhids</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Frieſland,</hi> the Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Frieſland,</hi> and Rear-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Van Saen,</hi> and the number of their fleet ſo impaired, that of above an hundred Ships there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned but eighty into harbour. The <hi>Dutch</hi> who hitherto ſtill boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Victory, gave now ſenſible ſigns of the Engliſh having the better, by leaving their harbours and rodes undefended; ſo that Sir <hi>Robert Holmes</hi> ſhortly after this fight, ſails into the <hi>Ulie,</hi> and with one fifth-rate Frigate, ſome Ketch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and fireſhips, there burnt an hundred and ſixty ſail of <hi>Dutch</hi> Veſſels.</p>
            <p>But neither was this nor the laſt blow ſo fatall as to keep the <hi>Dutch</hi> from Sea, for about the end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears again with a ſtronger fleet
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59474:28"/>then before, ſtretching along the back of the <hi>Goodwin</hi> ſands, for the <hi>French</hi>-coaſt, with deſigne to have joyned the Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> who with about forty ſail of <hi>French</hi> ſhips lay at <hi>Rochel</hi> ready to come to their aſſiſtance: The Engliſh fleet having advice, made after them with ſuch diligence, that they were forced to ſtand in for <hi>Bulloign</hi>-road, and there very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly eſcaped a new Engagement, by reaſon of the weather, which growing extremely tempeſtuous, conſtrained the Engliſh to bear away for <hi>S. Hellens Bay,</hi> the place of rendevouz, and the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtation to hinder the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch:</hi> In the mean while the <hi>Ruby</hi> a <hi>French</hi>-ſhip of fifty four guns, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Monſieur le Roche</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by foul weather from the reſt of the fleet, miſtaking the enemies white-flag for their own, fell in amongſt the Engliſh, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59474:28"/>after ſome ſtout reſiſtance, was taken, and the Captain made Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, but in complement to his valour, was afterward diſmiſſed: And now <hi>De Ruyter</hi> falling ſick, was forced to return to <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> leaving the care and charge of the <hi>Dutch</hi> fleet to <hi>Van Neſs;</hi> But the States finding the ſeaſon far ſpent, and the weather ſtormy and tempeſtuous, commanded their fleet home.</p>
            <p>After that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet was returned into harbour, and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> recovered of his ſickneſs, ſome grudgings and animoſities ariſen betwixt him and <hi>Van Trump</hi> during the late actions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding partly (as it was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) from the byaſs of their differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing factions, the former being a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared re-publican, and the latter a favourer of the intereſt of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who was not then advanced to the dignity of Stat-holder;) broke forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59474:29"/>ſuch open debate, that they mutually accuſed and blamed each other, for the ill ſucceſs and miſcarriages of the paſt Summers actions; but Admiral <hi>De Ruyter</hi> highly eſteemed by the States for his Valour, prudence and fingular conduct, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the favour of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Party, ſo far prevailed with his Maſters, that ſeveral Sea-Commanders were put to death for cowardiſe, and himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with greater power and authority then before.</p>
            <p>About the end of this year 1666. the Dutch being weary of the vaſt expences, and weakned by the great loſſes of the war, and the Engliſh much diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the burning of the City of <hi>London,</hi> which happened in <hi>September;</hi> both ſeemed inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to an accomodation; and overtures of peace thereupon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſet on foot on either
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59474:29"/>ſide; which ſeemed to ſome who thought themſelves wiſe very hopeful.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of the Spring <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was again ſpeeded out to Sea, and in <hi>April</hi> 1667, made an attempt with a good Fleet upon Brunt-Iſland, a Town in the Scottiſh firth, intending to have landed and ſpoyled the Countrey; but by the vigilant care, and conduct of the Earl of <hi>Rothoes,</hi> Chancellour of that Kingdom, with the Trained Bands of the Countrey, he was bravely repulſed with loſs.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>De Ruyter</hi> to amuſe the Engliſh (who in a ſmall Fleet were at ſea) ſent off a detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of twenty five ſail of ſhips to cruiſe to the Northward, who on the third of <hi>June</hi> falling in with Nineteen Sail of Engliſh Frigats off of <hi>Hull,</hi> began a furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and bloudy conflict, which was ſo ſtoutly and obſtinately
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59474:30"/>maintained on both ſides, that from twenty five the <hi>Dutch</hi> were reduc't to fourteen ſail, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> from nineteen to fifteen.</p>
            <p>Shortly after he made an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon ſome Neighbouring parts of <hi>Harwich,</hi> having put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoar three thouſand men near <hi>Felſton-cliff,</hi> and commanded two thouſand of them to make an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault upon <hi>Langward-Fort,</hi> which was twice eſſayed, the firſt laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about three quarters of an hour, and the other one quarter; but at laſt with the loſſe of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men, they were forced to retreat in ſo much haſte and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, that they left behinde them all their ladders: whileſt theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions continued at <hi>Langward-fort,</hi> a party of twelve hundred <hi>Dutch</hi> being poſted at the cliff their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-place, to ſecure and make good their retreat, were attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Trained Bands of the Countrey under the Command of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59474:30"/>the Earl of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> being ſupplied with freſh recruits from the Fleet, a very ſmart skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh continued betwixt them till ten of the night; but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> horſe then coming in ſight, the <hi>Dutch</hi> thought it ſafeſt to quit the Land, and ſo as ſoon as their boats were afloat, in great haſte they embarqued, and returned to their Fleet.</p>
            <p>The day following this defeat at <hi>Langward-Fort, de Ruyter</hi> with the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet was purſued by Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> and Sir <hi>Joſeph Jordan</hi> with about twenty ſail of ſmall Frigats; but whether <hi>De Ruyter</hi> finding his Orders limited, or for the reaſons above-hinted, notwithſtanding he had a much ſtronger Fleet, kept at diſtance, and carefully avoided engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; taking his courſe through the channell for the Weſtern parts of <hi>England:</hi> In his paſſage he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared before <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59474:31"/>knowing the ſtrength of the place, and finding the Countrey in arms, he only ſhewed himſelf there, and ſo continued his voyage to the Weſtern coaſts.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Devonſhire</hi> he endeavoured to have landed ſome men at <hi>Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> but the Militia of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey being ready to receive them, ſo warmly ſaluted them with ſome Volleys of ſmall ſhot, that they were forced with all ſpeed to betake themſelves back again to their ſhips. The Admiral de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing to effect any thing here by force, ſent off a boat with a white flag, deſiring leave to come aſhoar to buy freſh proviſions, but it was denied him by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Officers that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded there; alledging that no ſuch permiſſion could be granted without the conſent and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Commander in chief, who then was abſent: <hi>De Ruyter</hi> in this manner diſappointed of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59474:31"/>his intent at <hi>Wenbury,</hi> came with his whole Fleet before <hi>Couland</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and having anchored within musket ſhot of the ſhoar; ſent off twelve boats full of men with deſigne of landing, whilſt he in the mean time played on the land with his great guns from aboard: but the Foot of the Countrey, that were poſted there, purpoſely to oppoſe their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, charged them ſo briskly, that they were forced to put off again without effecting an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing.</p>
            <p>By this time <hi>De Ruyter</hi> being informed from <hi>Holland</hi> of the progreſs of the Treaty of Peace, which now was in a tendency to a ſpeedy concluſion, not willing with new hoſtilities to retard that which was ſo heartily deſired by both parties; relented a little in the ardour of his proceedings, and began to heal the wounds which he had formerly made, by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59474:32"/>prudent application of the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick plaiſters of neceſſity and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; excuſing ſome hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as thereto enjoyned by his Commiſſion, and others as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted without his Order: And to that purpoſe ſent off two of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers with a flag of truce, who being brought before Sir <hi>Jonathan Trelawny,</hi> who commanded in chief under the Earl of <hi>Bath</hi> in theſe parts, and having made the complement and apologies of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dmiral, deſired in his name a conference with ſome Engliſh aboard, for whoſe ſafe coming and returning, he was ready to engage the faith of the Seven Provinces. Sir <hi>Jonathan</hi> having herewith adviſed the Earl of <hi>Bath,</hi> by his Order <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was viſited aboard of his own Ship, by the ſame Sir <hi>Jonathan Trelawny,</hi> Major <hi>Sparks,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Windham.</hi> The Admiral upon their approach courteouſly came
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59474:32"/>over his Ships-ſide, met, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them in their boat, where after mutuall ſalutations, having renewed the Apologies formerly made by his meſſengers; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited them aboard, received them with a ſalute of Ordinance, and entertained them with the Chief Officers of his Fleet at a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent dinner in the great Cabbin: During which he gave honourable demonſtrations of love and eſteem for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and frequently repeated the expreſſions of the great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he had for his Majeſty and Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> and real and hearty wiſhes for a ſolid and permanent correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt both Nations, lamenting the great damages and loſs which acorued to both by ſo ruinating a War. The Engliſh entertained his civilities with reciprocal returns of honour and kindeneſs, and having offered
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59474:33"/>him ſupplies of all neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for his own Table, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing more untill the peace ſhould be concluded; they took their leave, having been firſt aſſured by him, that no more hurt ſhould be done to the Countrey whilſt he remained on theſe Coaſts. The Earl of <hi>Bath</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward preſented him with ſuch proviſions and neceſſaries, as the Countrey and ſeaſon of the year afforded; which he courteouſly received, and in ſigne of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude fired ſeveral guns, and ſo departed: but notwithſtanding the promiſes of indemnity gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, after his departure from <hi>Plymouth,</hi> two of his Fleet, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing toward <hi>Foy,</hi> for ſome time lay annoying and battering the harbour and ſhoar with great ſhot, till having received dammage in their hulls, and one of them having loſt his main topmaſt, they deſiſted and went
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59474:33"/>off; whether this was by the Generals Order or not, is not known; there having been no enquiry ever made in the action, by reaſon of the peace that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly followed; but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that <hi>De Ruyter</hi> had no hand in it.</p>
            <p>This long expected Peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Breda</hi> the 21 of <hi>June,</hi> and at length the 14th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1667. ratified in <hi>England,</hi> rather by the exigency and neceſſity of the times, than the intire and full ſatisfaction of both parties, as appeared within few years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, gave reſpite to both Nations to breathe a little, and recruit their mutual paſt loſſes by induſtrious proſecuting their traffick, the hugg'd darling of both people: and to conſider in cold blood what had been done amiſſe by either ſide, during the War, that from ſo ſeaſonable a peace, they might pick the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59474:34"/>means of future reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And now <hi>De Ruyter</hi> having ſafely reconducted his Fleet into harbour, was received by the States with thanks and honours ſuitable to his merit, and with the univerſal acclamations and applauſe of the Countrey; and was judged by all diſcreet men to have underſtood as well the meaſures of a General in that Common-wealth as any who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, by his never giving way to the tranſports of vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, or rage in the heat of action, but by timely retreat or advantagious fighting; like the Roman <hi>Fabius Maximus, Cunctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do reſtituit rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The States having now no more need of ſo eminent a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander at ſea, the great and dreadfull War being over, but occaſion ſtill of a wiſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed Stateſman at home; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Heer De Ruyter</hi> with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59474:34"/>no leſs expectation into their Councils of difficult affairs, then they had formerly impowred him as General at ſea: wherein he ſo anſwered their hopes; that during the four years peace, or rather ceſſation of arms betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> he gave ſo ſignal proofs of his prudence, that they were only fain to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with his being at home; becauſe they could not finde a Succeſſour for him abroad which the buſineſſe of the year 1672. ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently required.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King in <hi>anno</hi> 1671. with a conſiderable army came to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> this progreſſe in a time of peace being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with great preparations for War, gave apprehenſions to all his Neighbours, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the States of the United Provinces, who ſuſpecting that his approach ſo near them, was to ſhew them the rod with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59474:35"/>which he intended to chaſtiſe the rudeneſs and inſolency which the States were ſaid to have uſed towards his Majeſty; began to arm, and make ready for their own defence. The King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> likewiſe ſeeing his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and moſt dangerous compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titors ſo buſy and earneſt at work, the deſigne of which was not as yet made publick; thought it time to look to the ſecurity of his ſubjects, and to put his Kingdoms out of danger of a ſurpriſe: and ſo at the ſame time (as by an influence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny) moſt States of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeemed to prepare for war. The <hi>French</hi> who pretended to teach civility and good manners to thoſe, who oftentimes are not willing to learn; thought the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſtood in need of ſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments; and the partial and ſlow performances made by the States to the King of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:59474:35"/>and his ſubjects, of the Articles of their laſt Peace, and the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of the <hi>Dutch</hi> fiſhing, ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Engliſh ſeas, and more lately in their rivers, being neither ſo well adjuſted, nor digeſted, as might ſtand with the honour and ſecurity of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt; the King herewith provoked, and by reviling Pamphlets againſt his Royal Perſon, joyned with the <hi>French</hi> King in a ſtrict League of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing by arms their mutual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions againſt the <hi>Dutch:</hi> And having firſt friendly demanded ſatisfaction of the paſt abuſes by his Embaſſadour Sir <hi>George Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> his Majeſty reſolved to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon them to their duty by a more effectual Method.</p>
            <p>On the thirteenth of <hi>January,</hi> two parties meeting, and the Dutch refuſing to ſtrike, there followed an engagement, and this firſt blow being thus given,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59474:36"/>the King of Great Brittain pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth his Declaration againſt the States of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to this effect; That the diſſatisfaction which his Majeſty had from the carriage of the States General of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces towards him, for ſome years paſt, being ſuch, that he could no longer without diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his own honour, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the indignation raiſed in him by a treatment too unſuitable to the great obligations which he and his Predeceſſours had ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally heaped upon them; He was reſolved to declare war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, forbidding all his Subjects to hold correſpondence with them upon pain of death. This Declaration being with the uſuall ſolemnities proclaimed in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the French King with actions previous to a rupture with that Crown alſo: he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59474:36"/>laid great taxes and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes upon all Dutch goods in his kingdom, and raiſed an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of fifty <hi>per cent.</hi> upon ſalt, and other merchandiſes of <hi>France</hi> exported by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all herrings, ſpices, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods imported into his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions by them: prohibiting all his ſubjects to lade any bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy aboard of any <hi>Holland</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Veſſells, and ſhortly after publickly, and in good earneſt declared war.</p>
            <p>The States of <hi>Holland</hi> foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtorm which now began to break upon them, had ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified themſelves with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull alliances of <hi>Spain, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> that they ſeemed not unequally matched with their mighty enemies in ſo great a conjunction: ſo that in the year 1672. the greateſt part of the States of Chriſtendome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came involved in a bloody and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59474:37"/>expenſive War, which is not yet ended.</p>
            <p>Matters thus advancing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward action, the Dutch who were not behinde in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, but wanting a head, reſolved to gratifie both Kings in the choice of their General, and ſo in a full Aſſembly of the States, the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly elected <hi>Generalliſſimo</hi> of all their Forces both by Sea and Land, for that years expedition, with promiſe to renew his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority after expiration, during life: and <hi>Jan De Wit</hi> and the <hi>Rereward van Putten</hi> (the two unfortunate brothers that were afterward barbarouſly murthered in a tumult of the incenſed rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the <hi>Hague</hi>) with ſome others, appointed as Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to aſſiſt him: Under him <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was made Lieutenant-Admiral, whoſe power (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of his many tried
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59474:37"/>ſervices, ſuch is the fear of that State of an abſolute authority) was ſtinted, having the <hi>Rereward Van Putten</hi> placed over him by the States as a check and curb: and conſidering the foreward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Engliſh in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, was ordered with all expedition to haſten with his Fleet to Sea.</p>
            <p>His Royall Highneſs the <hi>Duke of York,</hi> whoſe former ſucceſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Dutch had rendred his very name more terrible to that people, than the wonders of others, being at Sea with the Engliſh Fleet commanded by himſelf in chief, and the Earl of <hi>Sandwich</hi> Admiral of the Blew; and having joyned the <hi>French</hi> with the white flag under the Command of the Count <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> which all together made a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Navy, of about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty ſail, great and ſmall: In <hi>May</hi> 1672. made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59474:38"/>the Coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> in ſearch of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, then likewiſe at Sea, Commanded by <hi>De Ruyter, Van Ghent</hi> and <hi>Banckert;</hi> and having had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral views of the enemy, but no opportunity of fighting, which the cautious <hi>De Ruyter</hi> always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, according to his politick <hi>Maximes,</hi> without ſome appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent advantage; but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at this juncture, when the States had ſo much lying at ſtake, not thinking it ſafe to quit his ſands: his Highneſs with the whole Fleet returned to the Coaſt of <hi>England,</hi> and came to anchor in <hi>Southwold Bay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Ruyter</hi> (in the mean while) who was ſeldome out in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, concluding that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining of an Engagement would certainly be by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> interpreted fear, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently breed in them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their enemy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59474:38"/>ſecurity, reſolved to come up with them before he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected: and being by his ſcouts advertiſed in what poſture the Engliſh fleet lay, and having the winde favourable at E. N. E. weighed anchor from behinde his banks with his whole Fleet and on <hi>May</hi> 29th. by five of the clock in the morning came in ſight of the Royall Fleet, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected, that ſeveral Ships were forced to cut their cables in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, to put themſelves in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of fighting, and about eight in the morning fell in with them. The fight began be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Earl of <hi>Sandwich</hi> in the <hi>Royall James</hi> with the blew Squadron, and <hi>Van Ghent,</hi> whilſt his Royall Highneſs in the <hi>Prince</hi> with the Red, engaged <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> and the Count <hi>De Eſtree</hi> with the French, and white Squadron, <hi>Banckert.</hi> The fight was terrible and bloody, eſpecially between
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59474:39"/>the blew Squadron and <hi>Van Ghent,</hi> who in the beginning of the battel was ſhot to death. The brave Earl of <hi>Sandwich</hi> who was reſolved to pawn his life for his honour, being engaged in the middle of the <hi>Dutch</hi> with a few ſhips; the <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and others of his Squadron, having ſtood off to gain the weather-gage, and the Duke in hot action with <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> overpowerd with a number of men of War and fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and a hardy Dutch Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Adrian Brackell,</hi> having laid him aboard athwart the haſs; yet ſtill continued the fight with ſuch unſhaken courage, that he ſunk two of three of the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips that had grapled with him, and forced the Dutch Captain to call for quarter: but at laſt his ſhip being unhappily fired by a third Fireſhip, was burnt, and he himſelf with many perſons of quality bravely, but unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59474:39"/>periſhed; to the grief of the King his Maſter, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable regret of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; having left to poſterity an immortal proof, that Valour crowned with honour, does not ſhrink, but ſwells by its reward. <hi>Haddock</hi> his Captain though wounded, eſcaped by ſwimming, till he was taken up. This hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the afternoon, when thoſe ſhips of the blew-ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, that had ſtood off, having got the winde, bore down upon the Dutch, and aſſiſted the Duke who preſſed <hi>De Ruyter</hi> ſo ſtraitly, that towards the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he gave way, and ſtood o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for the Dutch Coaſt, and was purſued by the Duke all night. In this Engagement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the loſſe of the Noble Earl of <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and his ſhip, the <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Royall Catherine,</hi> two great ſhips on the Engliſh ſide were taken, Captain <hi>Dighy</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59474:40"/>Commander of the firſt being killed, and Sir <hi>John Chichely</hi> of the latter made priſoner, but were both ſhortly after regained by the Engliſh priſoners aboard, who forced and overcome their guards. On the Dutch ſide, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Van Ghent</hi> was ſlain, moſt of their great ſhips miſerably torn, and two of them ſunk, and one of fourty eight guns Captain <hi>Elderſon</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Commander taken, many more were miſſing, of which no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular account can be given. The <hi>Dutch</hi> with confidence pleaſed themſelves to brag of a Victory with the accuſtomed ſolemnities of rejoycing; and imputed much of the Engliſh loſs to the French ſeperating from the reſt of the Fleet that day, about noon; but it is certain that the Duke ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving purſued them to their own Coaſt, and having next day in vain offered battel, kept the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59474:40"/>ſeas, and could bring them to no more action this year.</p>
            <p>The advice of the prevailing progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> on the one hand, and the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> on the other, which put the States in much apprehenſion, and the people in great fright and confuſion; being brought to <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> as he rode with his Fleet at the Oyſter-bank; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned his haſtening from thence to <hi>Blanckenburgh,</hi> there to put aſhoar a great part of his men to be employed at land, where the danger then ſeemed moſt preſſing: And whilſt he continued there with a Fleet half mann'd to ſecure the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Fleet, which was then look't for; the <hi>Duke of York</hi> kept at ſea, ſometime cruiſing, ſometime at anchor on the <hi>Doggerbank,</hi> in very bad weather, with intention either to ſeize that Fleet, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59474:41"/>voke the Dutch to a New En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement by their attempting to defend them. About this time the tumult of the untractable people who imputed all their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities to the errours of their Governours, grew every where ſo high, that it ſeemed to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a diſſolution of Government; eſpecially at <hi>Dort,</hi> where the <hi>Burghers</hi> armed in a great body having ſurrounded the houſe where the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> ſate at dinner, with the Magiſtrates of the place; ſent ſome of their Officers with a form of writing, containing a New Election of his Highneſſe to be hereditary Stat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of the Common-wealth, with a renunciation of all mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Acts and Edicts made by the <hi>Loveſtein</hi> faction to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; threatning the Magiſtrates with the loſſe of their lives, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they preſently ſigned it: This peremptory deſire the Magiſtrates
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59474:41"/>durſt not refuſe, but preſently ſigned the Writing, and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the Oath formerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from the Prince, never to accept any ſuch dignity for the future by the contrary and ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party: and this tumultuary procedure had the influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other Corporations, that moſt did the like; ſo that at length it advanced ſo far as to be publickly ratified and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the States; ſo great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der many times by a guiding providence is produced from greateſt confuſion.</p>
            <p>In the rage of this unruly multitude <hi>De Ruyter</hi> himſelf there celebrated tutelary and guardian, though then at ſea, for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence hardly eſcaped their fury; for a company of common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple having mutined into a body beſet his houſe in the New Iſland of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and if they had not been hindred by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59474:42"/>had plundered and ſackt it: this was ſo ſtrange when no previous ſet diſcourſe (that is known) did winde up the Jack to ſuch a revolution; that it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us another eaſy and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous remark, that men when they are mad, are never wiſe.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>York</hi> having for many weeks kept his ſtation, and ſuffered very foul weather on the <hi>Dogger-bank;</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> at <hi>Blanckenburgh,</hi> without any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of fighting; the long wiſhed for <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Fleet (which the Duke hoped might give occaſion to a new tryal) at length ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared near the Coaſt of <hi>Holland. De Ruyter</hi> by his advice-boats in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of this, thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged to uſe his utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, for the ſecurity of ſo great a concern: weighed from <hi>Blanckenburgh,</hi> and with a Fleet ill-mann'd, and in bad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fighting; ſlid along the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59474:42"/>ſhoar, without being diſcovered by the Engliſh; met the Fleet, and ſafely conducted them into <hi>Delfzey</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Emms.</hi> The <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Briſtol</hi> two Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Frigats, being then upon the ſcout, came up with them, and had ſome little encounter; but the windes was high, and the ſea ſo rough, that no booty could be gained. The Duke having now loſt all hopes of alluring the <hi>Dutch</hi> to any more action this year, left Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> with a ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of ſhips to keep the ſeas, and diſturb their fiſhing, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the reſt of the fleet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home.</p>
            <p>The torrent of the French con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts at land being now ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtopt, and the tumult and, rage of the people quieted, the affairs of Sea came next in play; In the preparations for which, the vigilant <hi>De-Ruyter</hi> with much diligence employed the winter
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59474:43"/>(which happened by reaſon of its openneſs, to be very favourable to the <hi>Dutch</hi>) propoſing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reaſonable advantages, if he could have a Fleet in readineſs next ſpring at Sea, before the coming of the <hi>French,</hi> which he effected. For in <hi>May</hi> 1673. with a ſtrong and well-appointed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy commanded by himſelf, <hi>Van Trump</hi> and <hi>Banckert,</hi> he was out again at Sea, and in the mouth of the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, by ſinking of ſeveral great Ships in the narrow paſſages of the Channel, called the <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground,</hi> to have ſtopped and blockt up the mouth and entry of the river; but the breadth of that channel, and the commodiouſneſs of others, rendred his attempts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in vain.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> who for this Years Expedition Commanded the Royal Navies, lying at the <hi>Buoy of the Nore,</hi> with part
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59474:43"/>of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> fleet (the <hi>French</hi> being not as yet arrived) when <hi>De Ruyter</hi> appeared, was hindred by the windes to get out; but afterwards having with much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty put to Sea, and made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Dutch: De Ruyter</hi> not ſwerving from his former mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, thinking he gained enough when he did not loſe, warily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired behinde the banks, thoſe impregnable ſea-ramparts, ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at that time any engagement: The Prince ſeeing this, ſtood with his fleet for the <hi>Streights</hi> off <hi>Calais,</hi> with intention to meet the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Portſmouth</hi> fleets; whom af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort ſtay, he having joyned at <hi>Dungean neſs,</hi> with the whole fleet, returned for the coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>May</hi> 26. 1673. arrived before <hi>Schonvelt</hi> where <hi>de Ruyter</hi> lay with his fleet.</p>
            <p>The winde and Sea then unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, allowed no fair opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of fighting, but the twenty
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59474:44"/>eighth in the morning, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fair, and a freſh gale, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Prince to action: <hi>De Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſtill kept his ſtation where the great ſhips could not approach: and the Prince reſolving by all means poſſible to draw him to an engagement, ſent off thirty five ſail of ſmall Frigats to provoke him to battel: The <hi>Dutch</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expectation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> in excellent order came forth, and boldly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred this Van-guard of the fleet with ſuch hot ſervice, that they being forced a little to yield, diſordered the reſt of the Royal Navy: The fight continued deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately on both ſides, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> with mutuall emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion behaving themſelves brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with ſo much eagerneſs, that they entangled each other, and gave ſome advantage to the enemy: For the Valiant Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi> being peſtered amongſt the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59474:44"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> ran foul of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fregat, and was entangled with a fireſhip; and was no ſooner got clear, but the obſervant <hi>De Ruyter</hi> laying hold of the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, bore down upon him with his whole Squadron, and gave him freſh occaſion to ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his Valour: The Earl with his ſhips that were with him, received the Admirall with no leſs reſolution then he was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqued, and maintained a bloudy fight, with equal ſucceſs, till both being ſufficiently battered, the night put an end to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> returned to their lurking holes: In this Fight <hi>de Ruyter</hi> loſt only the Ship called the <hi>Debenter,</hi> and had killed the Vice-Admſral <hi>Schram,</hi> Rear-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Ulugh,</hi> and ſix Captains: After the old manner both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties claimed the honour of the Victory; The <hi>Dutch</hi> becauſe they had repulſed the Aſſailants, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59474:45"/>the Engliſh becauſe they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Dutch</hi> to their banks of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; but both fleets were much damnified.</p>
            <p>The next three days were ſpent in mending and re-fitting their ſhattered ſhips, which the <hi>Dutch</hi> had better opportunity to perform (having all neceſſaries from their ſtores at hand) then the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who were ſo remote from their own Coaſt; So that <hi>de Ruyter</hi> knowing well the advantage, in the begining of <hi>Iune</hi> put out again, and by his approach allarmed the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who had not as yet got into ſuch readineſs; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they preſently put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a poſture of engaging, obſerving the motion of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> which <hi>de Ruyter</hi> perceiving drew all his fleet into a line, reaching three leagues, and ſo came to an anchor, expecting the coming unto the fleet of the <hi>Heers Boſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velt, Van der Meyden, Moregnault,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:59474:45"/>and <hi>Van der Vierſe</hi> the Deputies of the States General; who being arrived and in a Council of War having approved his intent of fighting, and afterward return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again aſhoar; on the fourth of <hi>June, De Ruyter</hi> with his whole Fleet, was by eleven of the clock again under ſail, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly towards the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, who kept their old ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> Admiral of the Engliſh blew ſquadron, who had the Van, not believing that the Dutch intended to fight, but only as before to change their rode; made no great haſte to bear up, and ſo loſt the winde; and being much preſſed by the <hi>French,</hi> as they by the Prince in the rear, who were all ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to come to blows; he was put in ſome little diſorder. The two Fleets for ſome time fought ſtoutly, eſpecially where the Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59474:46"/>Spragg</hi> engaged, till the Prince finding the diſadvantage of the winde, with the red and white ſquadrons ſtood away <hi>N W. De Ruyter</hi> thinking it was to get the winde, which he was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to loſe, did the like, and left <hi>Van Trump</hi> with the reſt of the Fleet in a ſharp conflict with <hi>Spragg</hi> and <hi>Oſſory.</hi> The day began to cloſe before the ſhot on either ſide betwixt the Prince and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> began to do exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: but at length the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh muſt confeſs, that to their great wonder, they firſt learned here, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> powder was ſtronger and the guns longer than their own. So Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi> having ſhifted himſelf from the <hi>Royal Charles</hi> into the <hi>Old Soverain,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> rejoyned the Fleet, they fought at diſtance moſt part of the night, and by break of day both Fleets being out of ſight of each
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59474:46"/>other, the Prince with the loſs of many men, and diſabled ſhips, made for the <hi>Thames;</hi> and <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with little loſs having had the advantage of the winde and a diſtant fight, ſtood back for his old ſtation on the Coaſt of <hi>Zeland. De Ruyter</hi> in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gave evident proof that he knew when it was time to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue as well as retreat, and that he never turned his back but with intent to ſhew his face.</p>
            <p>It was now the twentieth of <hi>July</hi> before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> were in condition again to viſit the <hi>Dutch</hi> Coaſts, and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſcovered <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with his Fleet eight leagues off of the Coaſt of <hi>Zealand,</hi> and in poſture of Fighting, the Royall Navy expected an Engagement, but wiſe <hi>De Ruyter</hi> who always fought after his own manner, knew well the importance of ſo great a triall, and that the affairs
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59474:47"/>of his Countrey ſo embarraſſed on all hands, did not require the hazarding of the intereſt and honour of his Maſters, or of himſelf, without ſome probable hopes of ſaving of both; ſtood in nearer the ſhoar, and bore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way along the Coaſt, declining all engagement untill the one and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>On the twentieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> being informed that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet were about <hi>Goree,</hi> made thither, and towards the evening diſcovered them: but being then late, thought beſt not to attacque them that night: In the mean time <hi>De Ruyter</hi> according to his ordinary conduct improving the benefit of the darkneſs, ſtood in cloſe to the ſhoar, and bearing up before next morning, gained the winde of the Engliſh, and by ſeven of the Clock bore down
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59474:47"/>upon them freſhly. The <hi>Prince</hi> upon this, changing his courſe, ſtood away S. W. and the <hi>French</hi> who had the Van engaged <hi>Banckert,</hi> the Prince in the middle, <hi>De Ruyter</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> in the rear, (after the old manner) <hi>Van Trump.</hi> This Fight was ſo managed between the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> as if both parties being by ſome ſecret inſtinct ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted that this was to be the laſt, reſolved to prove their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and laſt effects of fortitude and conduct among the <hi>French,</hi> Capt. <hi>Martel</hi> behaved himſelf bravely: <hi>Banckert</hi> ſent off a few ſhips to wait the <hi>French</hi> motion, and with the reſt of his ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron came in to the aſſiſtance of <hi>De Ruyter</hi> againſt the Prince, who for ſome time valiantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed their broadſides, and behaved themſelves with equal courage and ſucceſs. Sir <hi>Edward Spragg</hi> and <hi>Van Trump</hi> (the two
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59474:48"/>declared Competitiours and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals for honour) with their ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons in the mean time perſiſted in action with ſuch determinate reſolution, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> avow the like never to have been ſeen, their own two ſhips having without touching of a ſail ſtrangely endured the fury of three full hours unceſſant batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But Sir <hi>Edward Spraggs</hi> Ship the <hi>Prince,</hi> having loſt her maſts, and being ſo fearfully torn, as to be unfit for more ſervice, with his flag diſplayed in his boat, he ſhifted aboard off the <hi>St. George;</hi> and finding her like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſabled, as he was leaving of her to get into the <hi>Royall Charles,</hi> a cruel ſhot funk his boat, and left him helpleſs in the Ocean, whoſe power being grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that of <hi>Van Trump;</hi> by his death chill'd that heat of courage, which <hi>Trump</hi> could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have cooled above water:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59474:48"/>His death was by all, even the Dutch themſelves bewailed, who acknowledged him to have been a brave man, and valiant Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: His Ship couragiouſly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſtout Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi> (notwithſtanding all the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts that <hi>Van Trump</hi> made to be Maſter of her.) was ſafely towed off by the <hi>Hampſhire</hi> Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. The Prince and <hi>de Ruyter</hi> at this time finding themſelves at too great diſtance from the ſquadrons ſo hotly engaged, who ſtood both in need of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; as by mutual conſent, tacked both, and in friendly manner without firing, ſtood to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their reſpective friends: but <hi>de Ruyter</hi> having joyned <hi>Van Trump</hi> who was ſtill engaged, with the blew, before the Prince could could come in; fell upon the blew with renewed fury, intending to have totally out off that ſquadron from the reſt of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59474:49"/>Engliſh Fleet; but at length the Prince coming in time, broke in amongſt the Dutch with unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable force, and Captain <hi>Legg</hi> with his fireſhips, put them in great diſorder and confuſion; It was believed by all, that if the <hi>French</hi> had made their beſt uſe of that winde, <hi>de Ruyter</hi> and his Fleet could not ſo fairly (as they did) by the favour of the night, have taken their leave of this and all other publick action with the Engliſh, during this War. The loſſes in this laſt Fight were great on both ſides; many brave Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, and Vaſt number of men killed and wounded; but both ſo poſitively pretending to victory, it is hard to determine who had the better; yet the Dutch by Sir <hi>Edward Spraggs</hi> death think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their title good, made the whole Countrey ſo merry with the ringing noiſe of Victory: that the States changed the following
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59474:49"/>day of Humiliation into thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and in ſtead of faſting, drunk and ſung Pſalms.</p>
            <p>The ſingular prudence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Admiral <hi>de Ruyter</hi> in the ſeveral paſſages of this War, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him ſo uſeful to his Countrey (of whoſe tottering and decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate he ſeemed the <hi>Atlas</hi> and guardian) and ſo conſiderable to his enemies, who by experience found it not eaſy to triumph-over him; that notwithſtanding the powerful efforts made for that end, the ſucceſs of affairs remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo little inclined to either ſide, that the one had no reaſon to deſpair, nor the other to ſcorn the proſſers of accommodation; made way for a Treaty of peace with <hi>England;</hi> and the States of <hi>Holland</hi> catching their opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when the vigorous interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Crown, and Miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> concurred ſo pat with the publick good offices of their
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59474:50"/>friends in <hi>England:</hi> they ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually purſued the neceſſary and advantagious concern of peace with that kingdom, that by the frequent ſollicitations and buſy importunities of one and other, the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> did at length condeſcend to a peace with the Dutch: which was concluded at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> the Ninth of <hi>February,</hi> 1674. to the unſpeakable joy of the States, and perpetual renown of <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> in ſuch a pinching nick of time, that the Dutch had good reaſon to be thankfull for ſo ſeaſonable an accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Janus</hi> Temple being thus half ſhut, and the States General ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now but one way to look; reſolved to bend all their forces againſt the <hi>French,</hi> both by Sea and land: and knowing that the <hi>French</hi> would not adventure to meet them at Sea; being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59474:50"/>from the Engliſh; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it moſt convenient to moleſt their navigation, annoy their Coaſts, and deſtroy (as much as conveniently could be done) their Countrey and Plantations. In Order hereunto, they ſent out a great Fleet of ſixty ſix men of War, beſides victuallars, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and fireſhips, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Lieutenant Admirall <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> and <hi>Van Trump,</hi> with a flying Army of Land-forces, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Count <hi>William Van Horn.</hi> This Fleet joyned at their rendevous on the fourteenth of <hi>May</hi> 1674. ſet ſail from the <hi>Weel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> and having by a Squadron of fifteen men of War, allarmed all the Coaſt of <hi>Calais</hi> and <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> they paſſed along the Engliſh ſhoar, and <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> and come to anchor in <hi>Tourbay.</hi> Here after a great Councill of War, they divided the Fleet into two Squadrons; appointing one and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59474:51"/>twenty fail of Men of War, and fourty eight other Ships, with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies of Land-ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, under the Command of Old <hi>De Ruyter</hi> Admiral, <hi>Evertſe</hi> of <hi>Zealand</hi> Vice-Admiral, and young <hi>Engell de Ruyter</hi> Son of the other Rear-Admiral for the Weſtern French Iſlands; and <hi>Van Trump</hi> and the Count <hi>Horn,</hi> with the reſt of the fleet and Land-forces, for the Coaſt of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The deſigne ſo laid, was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly put in execution; for <hi>De Ruyter</hi> with his fleet on the 29. of <hi>May</hi> made ſail to the Weſtward, and ten days after <hi>Van Trump</hi> for the coaſt of <hi>France; de Ruyter</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing his courſe with fair windes, on the ninth of <hi>Iuly</hi> came in ſight of the <hi>Isle of Martenique,</hi> and the tenth arrived in the Bay called <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack:</hi> The <hi>French</hi> being advertiſed of their coming, appeared in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, marching towards the ſhoar, and the Dutch with ſome ſmall
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59474:51"/>ſhips that ſailed near the land, told them their errand, by firing ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them from aboard? this ſalute forced the <hi>French</hi> a little to retreat, and burn ſome houſes, which they thought ſtood in their way, and favoured the Enemy: In the afternoon a Council of War being held, a deſcent was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on, and <hi>de Ruyter</hi> having given the ſigne of landing, the land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces divided into 3. ſquadrons, under the Command of Col. <hi>Vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenhove,</hi> with 20 men to throw gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes for each Squadron, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly embarked in their boats and ſhalloops, and with great cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, notwithſtanding the <hi>French</hi> violent firing on them from their ſhips which they had aſhoar, and out of their woods, landed and made themſelves Maſters of a Bank, which the <hi>French</hi> had caſt up to prevent their landing, and forced the Enemy to retire to their Fort: <hi>De Ruyter</hi> perceiving
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59474:52"/>the Engagement hot, ſent off 1500. ſeamen to reinforce his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the <hi>French</hi> firing furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from behinde their ſhips, and battery, which they had raiſed, flanking the <hi>Dutch</hi> who ſtood na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to their ſhot, and whoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non did them little ſervice, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Evening beat them off again to their ſhips, with the loſs of many men, and ſeveral brave Officers, and ſo freed the Iſland at this time from further dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Ruyter</hi> after much loſs find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the attempt fruitleſs, left four ſhips to cruiſe thereabouts, and wait the coming of ſome Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allers expected from <hi>Holland,</hi> and next day ſailed to <hi>Dominico,</hi> there to take in freſh water, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, paſſing by <hi>Mevis</hi> and the <hi>Barmoodoes,</hi> and having mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually received and rendered ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, made ſail for <hi>Holland,</hi> and about
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59474:52"/>latter end of <hi>September,</hi> with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſucceſs in this expedition, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived ſafely at home, and <hi>Trump</hi> and <hi>Van-Horn</hi> having by ſeveral deſcents on <hi>Bell-Iſle,</hi> and other parts of that coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed and vexed the <hi>French,</hi> and plundered the country; and the fleet having after conducted and brought back from <hi>Spain</hi> the Count <hi>Van Horn,</hi> who went to negotiate at <hi>Madrid,</hi> with 18 ſail of the fleet (the reſt being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways imployed) in the latter end of <hi>November</hi> following, returned likewiſe to the <hi>Texell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the difficulty of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>Meſſina,</hi> ſo ſtrongly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by the <hi>French,</hi> requiring much of the care and Forces of <hi>Spain</hi> to be employed in <hi>Sicily,</hi> ſenſibly weakened the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of the States of <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the danger lay at their doors. The States there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being ſollicited by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59474:53"/>of <hi>Spain,</hi> that they might either give a neceſſary diverſion to the <hi>French,</hi> who in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt eſpouſed the quarrel, and endeavoured the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Meſſineſſes,</hi> and thereby hinder the progreſſe nearer home; or that they might effectually aid the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to the intire ſubduing of theſe Revolters, and ſo bring over to <hi>Flanders</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other inſtruments of war employed in theſe parts; In the beginning of 1675. reſolved to diſpatch their ſucceſſeful Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>De Ruyter,</hi> with a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fleet of Men of war into the <hi>Streights,</hi> to joyn the Prince <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſarchio</hi> Generall of the <hi>Spaniſh Armada</hi> for the effecting of that deſigne; accordingly about the latter end of <hi>Auguſt, de Ruyter</hi> with a fleet of 25. ſail, wyed from <hi>Schonvelt,</hi> and having ſtopt at <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz,</hi> and other places, by the way, in <hi>December</hi> following joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59474:53"/>
               <hi>Monteſarchio</hi> at <hi>Palermo</hi> with part of his Fleet, and after that he had ſtayed ſome time for thoſe of his Ships which then were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Naples</hi> from <hi>Argiers</hi> under the Command of Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>de Haen,</hi> and received them at the place of Rendevouz: They ſailed all together from <hi>Palermo</hi> to <hi>Melazzo,</hi> where <hi>de Ruyter</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had conference with the Duke of <hi>Ferrandina</hi> the Spaniſh Viceroy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> It was reſolved that the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet by Sea, and the Vice-roy by Land ſhould attacque and moleſt <hi>Meſſina,</hi> before that any further ſuccours did arrive there: In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that, <hi>de Ruyter</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of a Fleet of Ships laden with proviſions and neceſſaries for the beſieged who then were in great ſtraits by want, and not like long to ſubſiſt without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, being at ſea under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of a ſquadron of Men of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59474:54"/>War commanded by the <hi>Sieur de Queſny,</hi> made towards the fare of <hi>Meſſina</hi> to intercept and hinder their paſſage; and whileſt the Prince <hi>Monteſarchio</hi> left with ſome ſhips to guard the mouth of the fare, was ſeparated from the reſt of the Fleet, on the 29th of <hi>January,</hi> 1675. <hi>de Ruyter</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred the <hi>French</hi> off of <hi>Lipari,</hi> with a fleet not much odd in number to his own, having both between twenty and thirty ſail of Men of War a piece, beſides galleys, fireſhips, and other ſmall craft, and with much courage and bravery engaged them: The <hi>French</hi> received him with no leſs reſolution; ſo that there began a very brisk diſpute betwixt them, which continued all that day and the next, with conſiderable damage to their Ships and rigging, but no great loſſe of men, the fight having been at ſome diſtance: In this
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59474:54"/>engagement the <hi>French</hi> loſt one man of War, and two fireſhips, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> one Fregat, which being diſabled in the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Galleys were towing of her off for <hi>Palermo,</hi> ſunk, but the men were ſaved. The day following <hi>de Ruyter</hi> being advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the <hi>Sieur de Queſny</hi> by another way round the Iſland, unperceived by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> had conveyed the deſtin'd ſuccours into <hi>Meſſina;</hi> and foreſeeing well the bad conſequences of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, being much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with the ſlow proceedings of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> grave &amp; Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick circumſpection, and their conduct of affairs; thought it not convenient further to purſue the <hi>French,</hi> nor to abide longer in theſe quarters, (the ſix Moneths appointed by the States his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for that expedition being now expired) and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rejoyned <hi>Monteſarchio</hi> with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59474:55"/>his eight Spaniſh Men of War, he took his leave of him, in order to his returning home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>This ſudden departure threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> put the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roys of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples</hi> in great perplexity, and the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> in much trouble, who judged thereby the buſineſſe of <hi>Meſſina</hi> almoſt deſperate; ſo that all means poſſible were uſed by the Agents of <hi>Spain,</hi> to retain him in theſe parts; and particularly importunate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in <hi>Holland</hi> for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing the time of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which prevailed.</p>
            <p>New Orders from <hi>Holland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived at <hi>Naples,</hi> the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy the Duke <hi>de los Velos,</hi> fearing that <hi>de Ruyter</hi> might paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out touching there, and ſo miſſe of receiving of his Letters, of ſo great concern to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: ſent off the Dutch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59474:55"/>with ſome Galleys to meet him, and to acquaint him with the will of the States, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him to <hi>Naples:</hi> This occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned <hi>de Ruyters</hi> coming to <hi>Naples,</hi> where he was ſplendidly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Vice-roy; and in viſiting the City treated with the ſame honours as are uſually rendred to his own perſon, but haſtened again aboard. The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſent from <hi>Holland</hi> of his Commiſſion renewed, and a re-inforcement of his Fleet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, ſet him at work to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and puſh forward the ſlow and heavy march of the Spaniards in the execution of their Goun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils; and ſo having cruiſed with his Fleet ſome time at <hi>Palermo,</hi> and ſome time at <hi>Melazzo;</hi> and had conference with the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy of <hi>Sicily:</hi> It was condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, that <hi>Augusta,</hi> a place that held for the Rebels, ſhould be inveſted by Sea and Land, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59474:56"/>accordingly <hi>de Ruyter</hi> with his fleet made haſte for the <hi>Bay of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta,</hi> a place to him too ſatal for ſo famous a name; whileſt he was there, intelligence was brought him, that the <hi>French</hi> were at Sea; whereupon that night he ſailed, and next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got ſight of the Enemy, they being about the Cape <hi>Spartivento,</hi> and he himſelf with his fleet three Leagues from <hi>Auguſta:</hi> The morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was calm, ſo that he could not come up with the Enemy, but in the afternoon a freſh gale blowing from S. E. brought both fleets nearer together: <hi>De Ruyter</hi> being in the Van, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the body, and Vice-Admiral <hi>de Haen</hi> in the Rear of the fleet, which beſides the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but of ſeventeen <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, with other galleys, fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and ſmall craft; They bore down with great eagerneſs upon the <hi>French,</hi> conſiſting of thirty
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59474:56"/>Men of war, and ſeven fireſhips, with galleys, and other Tenders: About four in the afternoon the fight began, and laſted till ſeven, with obſtinate reſolution and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, betwixt the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> who ſuſtained the whole brunt of this Engagement; for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> did but little, only kept themſelves out of harms way, and did what miſchief they could at a diſtance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> had in this Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment three Ships ſo diſabled as to be towed off, and one Captain kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but ſmaller loſſes are undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable when the great <hi>De Ruyter</hi> fell; For here it was that preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>French</hi> at the latter end of the Fight, ſo as to make them give way; a bold bullet from the Enemies Fleet ſtopt him in his carreer; which having carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away part of his left foot, and broke his left leg above the ancle, threw him on the deck,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59474:57"/>ſo as by his fall he was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the head: The Fleet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſlackened ſail, and ſtood for the Bay of <hi>Syracuſa:</hi> The wounded General was carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoar for the more conveniency of cure; which then did not ſeem deſperate, but the greatneſs of his minde unacquainted with ſuch checks of fortune, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo that diſtemper of body; which it patiently bore, that the nineteenth of <hi>April</hi> having been ſpeechleſs a day before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween nine and ten of the Clock at night, in the Seveniteth year and Second Moneth of his Age, at the firſt violent ſummons of Fortune; yeelded his laſt Duty to Nature; and as he had lived, died in the embraces of beloved honour.</p>
            <p>This his Death, as it filled his friends and Countrey with grief and lamentation, and all men with pitty and regret, ſo
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59474:57"/>being a loſſe great enough to caſt the ballance of advantage even to the moſt forlorn and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing ſide; gave the <hi>French</hi> a Victory not equalled by their confederate Adverſaries, unleſs when laſt year Triumphant <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene</hi> the only Paragon of his worth and fame, upon a different Stage, played his laſt Act: which two great Champions much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in their Original (the one being born to a great ſhare of his honour, and the other to make all his own,) did ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble each other, in the courſe of their Lives and Fortune, and manner and Circumſtances of dying; that it ſeemed nature had framed them for two Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects whereon Fortune might ſhew her skill, in diſpencing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually her inclinations to great and powerfull adverſaries in the higheſt pitch of competition. For as either had been the conſtant
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59474:58"/>Favourite of their reſpective Maſters, and the often and long experieneed prop of their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hopes; the one at Land, and the other at Sea, ſo both fell by an interchanged great Shot, in ſuch a point of time, when their actions gave great hopes and confidence to their ſeveral Parties; and their death was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with remarkable and dangerous conſequences to either ſide: and had Fortune proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the beginning, and ſhould ſhe ſtill continue with ſo even and impartial a hand in all the occurrences and tranſactions, of this formidable war; both parties might have occaſion to celebrate their triumphs with tears, and with drawn ſtakes ſit down, and mutually confeſs, that</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Iam ſumus ergo pares.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:59474:58"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De Ruyter</hi> was a perſon (as moſt brave men have been) of a middle ſtature, a ſtrong and well compacted body, not fat, but fleſhy, of a gracefull and majeſtick countenance, his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect pleaſant and chearfull, not terrible by too much fierceneſs, nor by too great mildeneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awful; of a complexion ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine, and a conſtitution tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and healthfull; ſober in his diet, and moderate, though free in his words; neither ſullen with rigid and moroſe reſervedneſs, nor by loquacity affected or vain; his geſtures manly and natural; and generally of a frame of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſo even and harmonious, as rendred him ſedate and conſtant, and altogether free from the miſtakes and waverings that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company fickle and light natures, in the greater viciſſitudes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: He advanced to the height of Honour by the regular ſteps
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59474:59"/>of merit and patience, never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuning his deſtiny by untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and precipitant ambition; nor ſlighting or being out of the way when Fortune called him to preferment: which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by ſuch wiſe and prudent meaſures, as made him accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all; not ſtaining the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his great actions by vain-glorious oſtentation, and overweening pride; but by being dutiful to his ſuperiours, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his equalls, gratefull to his benefactors, affable and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to his inferiours; and in a word, obliging to all: he gained the love and eſteem of all that knew him; entertaining e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the meaneſt of the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of his low eſtate with that civility, that if in the top of honour, they enjoyed not the ancient familiarity of his baſer fortune, they eaſily ſaw, that it was his place and dignity, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59474:59"/>not the change of humour, that altered the ſtile. <hi>In fine,</hi> he was ſo good a man, ſo devout and pious a Chriſtian, ſo ſtout a Souldier, ſo wiſe, expert, and ſucceſsfull a General; and ſo faithfull, truſty, and honeſt a Lover of his Countrey, that he deſerves juſtly to be recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Poſterity, as an ornament of his Age, the darling of the Seas, and the delight and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Countrey.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59474:60"/>
            <head>Theſe Books are Sold by <hi>Dorm. Newman</hi> at the Kings Arms in the Poultrey.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Tachmas,</hi> Prince of <hi>Perſia,</hi> an hiſtorical Novel, which happened under the Sophy <hi>Seliman,</hi> who reigns at this day.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Gout, Written originally in the French Tongue by <hi>Theodor Turquet de May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne,</hi> Kt. Baron of <hi>Aubonne,</hi> Counſellour and Chief Phyſician to the late King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>Tho. Sherly</hi> Phyſician in Ordinary to his Majeſty. Whereto is added, Advice about Hypochoudriacal fits, By the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>A New and Eaſie Engliſh Grammar Dictionary and Nomenclator, Engliſh and Dutch.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of Devils proved to be the grand Apoſtacy of theſe latter times, An Eſſay tending to rectifie thoſe undue notions men have about <hi>Daemons</hi> and evil Spirits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nveyled,</hi> in behalf of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> giving particular Inſtances of ſuch (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt her profeſt Sons) as have ventured upon Innovations in her Doctrine, being a Vindication of Mr. <hi>Standiſh</hi> his Sermon before the King, and publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command; By a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>The whole Body of Arithmetick made Eaſie, wherein the Rules of that Art are briefly explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and illuſtrated with ſuch familiar examples as may reach the capacity of any that deſire to learn.</p>
            <p>Dr <hi>Robert Bayfields</hi> Anatomy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kitchin Phyſick,</hi> With Rules to prevent ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and cure diſeaſes by diet, and ſuch things as are daily ſold in the Market, By <hi>Tho Cocke.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is added, A Diſcourſe of Stoving.</p>
            <p>Letters of Advice from two Reverend Divines to a young Gentleman about a Caſe of Conſcience</p>
            <p>The <hi>School of the Heart</hi> in 47 Emblemes.</p>
            <p>Sixteen Sermons Preached on Sever all Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: By <hi>Edvv. Boys,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59474:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
